Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

■ pedro.harunari@uni.lu | # November 15th, 1995 | ★ pedroharunari.github.io/website/

Personal Profile

Currently, I hold a postdoctoral researcher position at the University of Luxembourg, working under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where I engaged in extensive research and teaching activities. As an active researcher in statistical physics, my focus is on understanding and taming fluctuations of systems outside thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. I am particularly interested in extending the description of stochastic thermodynamics in the presence of hidden degrees of freedom by pinpointing the relevant quantities, deriving practical expressions for real-world challenges, and connecting to the study of phase transitions, biophysics, chemical reaction networks, complex systems, and more.

Education

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Postdoctoral researcher

Dec 2022 - Current

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- · Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Doctorate in Physics Mar 2018 - Nov 2022

- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Carlos E. Fiore
- · Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- · Approved with the highest grades in every course
- · Teaching assistant experience during three semesters, both in graduate and undergraduate levels

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- One semester as teaching assistant
- · Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

List of Publications

8 articles published in internationally renowned journals and one preprint.

From Google Scholar: 109 citations, h-index 7.

Physical Review X **12**, 041026

IN Mamede, PE Harunari, BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings"

Physical Review E **105** (2), 024106

CE Fiore, PE Harunari, CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions"

Physical Review E **104** (6), 064123

PE Harunari, S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, "Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric interaction times"

Physical Review Research 3 (2), 023194

PE Harunari, CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, "Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump"

Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical **53** (37), 374001 2020

CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing nonequilibrium phase transitions"

March 23, 2023

Physical Review E 100 (1), 012104 2019

JM Encinas, PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase transitions in the inertial majority vote model"

Scientific reports 8 (1), 1-9 2018

PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority

vote model"

Physical Review E 96 (4), 042305 2017

Work Experience

(Post)Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer

Dec 2022

- Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg
- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

May 2022 - Jun 2022

Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Visiting researcher

Apr 2021 - Feb 2022

• Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.

· Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

University of Aalto Helsinki, Finland

Visiting researcher Dec 2021 - Jan 2022

· Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

Statistical Physics seminar series

online

Organizer

· 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across

Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Teaching assistant 2018 - 2020

- Thermodynamics (2020);
- Statistical Mechanics (2018 and 2019);
- Graduate level Statistical Mechanics (2018).

University of São Paulo São Paulo, Brazil

Undergraduate researcher

2015 - 2017

- · Research training program.
- Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

Skills_

Programming Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, ETEX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

Grants

FAPESP, grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE) 2021

FAPESP, grant of 4 years for the Doctorate without Masters degree program 2018

2017 FAPESP, grant for the Undergraduate research program

CNPq, grant for the Undergraduate research program 2016

MARCH 23, 2023

MECO 47 • Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions" Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society • Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	2022
Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society	
Brazilian Physical Society	
	Paulo, Braz
	202
National Statistical Physics Meeting Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ) • Talk: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"	online 202
Statistical Physics of Complex Systems The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP) • Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions"	Trieste, Italy
Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS)	online 202
Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society Italk: "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions"	online 202.
Stochastic Thermodynamics II Santa Fe Institute	online 202
 APS March Meeting American Physical Society Talk: "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations" 	online 202.
Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems Donostia International Physics Center	online
Statistical Physics Seminar Series University of São Paulo Ialk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR"	online 202
Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society Talk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties"	online 202
Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists Bad Honn Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation Poster: "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pump and its exact solution"	nef, German
	Paulo, Braz
series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects"	201
Physics Giants: Einstein Week series of talks organized by USP students Invited talk: "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics"	Paulo, Braz 201

Peer-review contributions

Spanish Llimited working proficiency

Portuguese Native proficiency

(3) Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical, (1) Journal of Physics Communications

March 23, 2023